<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY tex "TeX">
  <!ENTITY latex "LaTeX">
]>
<book id="phonix.xml" lang="en">
  <title>Phonix Phonological Transformation Language</title>
  <bookinfo>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright &copy; 2009-2010 Jesse Bangs.</para>
      <para>This manual and Phonix itself are licensed under the BSD license.</para>
    </legalnotice>
</bookinfo>
  <chapter label="" xreflabel="Phonix Phonological Transformation Language" id="Top">
    <title>Phonix Phonological Transformation Language</title>
    <para>This file documents a language for modeling phonological change.</para>
    <para>This is the manual for Phonix, a language for expressing diachronic and
synchronic phonological processes.</para>
    <para>$LastChangedDate: 2010-10-17 12:59:35 -0500 (Sun, 17 Oct 2010) $</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter label="1" id="Quick-Start">
    <title>Quick Start Guide</title>
    <para>You are a busy person. You have sound changes to apply and phonologies to
crunch and you do not have time to read a whole manual.</para>
    <para>This section is for you.</para>
    <para>Writing your first phonology in Phonix is very easy: all that you need to do is
open up a text file and type the following:</para>
    <screen>
import std.features
import std.symbols
</screen>
    <para>The first line above automatically adds the standard feature set to your
phonology. The second line adds the standard symbol set. Together, these
provide you with a set of contrastive features and phonetic symbols to allow
you express whatever phonological processes you desire. You can find out
exactly what these imports contain by reading <xref linkend="@code{std.features}"></xref> and
<xref linkend="@code{std.symbols}"></xref>.</para>
    <para>But you've only started. Your phonology contains rules and processes that
convert underlying forms to surface forms, and the first and most important
rule in your phonology is <emphasis>I-Nasal</emphasis>. This rule is expressed in English as:
"every front vowel must be /i/ if the next segment is /n/". (This is, perhaps,
not a very realistic rule, but we're doing this for the sake of simplicity.) In
Phonix, you will write this as such:</para>
    <screen>rule i-nasal
    [-cons +fr] =&gt; i / _ n
</screen>
    <para>A well educated phonologist such as yourself will immediately recognize the
notation being used here. The string <literal>[-cons +fr]</literal> is a <firstterm>feature
matrix</firstterm> that specifies non-consonantal front segments a.k.a. front vowels, and
the notation <literal>=&gt; i</literal> may be read as "becomes /i/". The portion following
the <literal>/</literal> is the <firstterm>context</firstterm>, and the context for this rule is <literal>_ n</literal>,
which we read as "when followed by /n/".</para>
    <para>If you didn't understand that, you should read <xref linkend="Rules"></xref>, which has a much
fuller explanation. You may also look at the <xref linkend="Romanian"></xref> for examples of
other Phonix rules.</para>
    <para>Save your phonology in a file called <filename>my.phonix</filename>. Let's assume that you
already have a file <filename>lexicon.txt</filename> with a list of underlying forms for your
transformations, with one word on each line. Conveniently, this is exactly the
format that Phonix uses. You can then apply your rules to your lexicon by
typing the following on the command line:</para>
    <para><command>phonix my.phonix -i lexicon.txt</command></para>
    <para>This will print the output of your sound changes to the screen, one word on
each line. Should you wish to have Phonix save them to a file, simply provide
the filename with <option>-o</option>:</para>
    <para><command>phonix my.phonix -i lexicon.txt -o output.txt</command></para>
    <para>This barely scratches the surface of what Phonix can do, but it should give you
an idea of how Phonix works and what you can do with it. There are many, many
more features in Phonix which the rest of this manual will describe.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter label="2" id="How-To-Use-Phonix">
    <title>How To Use Phonix</title>
    <para><firstterm>Phonix</firstterm> refers to the Phonix programming language for modeling
phonological processes, and informally to the program <filename>phonix</filename> that
interprets Phonix language files and applies the rules contained therein to
a lexicon.</para>
    <para>In order to use Phonix, you need two things:</para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>A <firstterm>Phonix file</firstterm> that contains the feature, symbol, and rule
declarations of the phonology you wish to model. Phonix files conventionally
have the extension <filename>.phonix</filename> or <filename>.phx</filename>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The lexicon for your phonology&mdash;the underlying or ancestral forms before
any rules or sound-changes are applied to them&mdash;written with the symbols
defined in your Phonix file. Phonix can read your lexicon from standard input
or from a file.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>The Phonix language is described in detail in <xref linkend="The-Phonix-Language"></xref>. This
section describes how to invoke <filename>phonix</filename> to run your phonology files.</para>
    <para>A basic invocation of Phonix looks like this:</para>
    <screen>
phonix <replaceable>phonix-file</replaceable> <replaceable>arguments</replaceable>
</screen>
    <para>The only required argument is the <replaceable>phonix-file</replaceable>, which is a file containing
a phonology definition. The following arguments are optional.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-i <replaceable>filename</replaceable></option></term>
        <term><option>--in <replaceable>filename</replaceable></option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The lexicon file from which underlying/ancestral forms are read to have the
Phonix rules applied to them. If this argument is not given, Phonix reads from
standard input.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-o <replaceable>filename</replaceable></option></term>
        <term><option>--out <replaceable>filename</replaceable></option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The filename to which to write output forms that the rules have applied to. If
this argument is not given, Phonix writes to standard output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-q</option></term>
        <term><option>--quiet</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When this option is present, Phonix doesn't print any errors except for fatal
error messages.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-d</option></term>
        <term><option>--debug</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When this option is given, Phonix writes a variety of diagnostic messages to
the standard error stream to aid in debugging your phonology.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-v</option></term>
        <term><option>--verbose</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When this option is given, Phonix logs verbosely to the standard error stream.
This creates all of the output generated by <option>-d</option>, plus more.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-w</option></term>
        <term><option>--warn-fatal</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When this option is given, certain conditions that normally produce a warning
will cause Phonix to immediately exit.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>Phonix requires some version of the Common Language Runtime, commonly known on
Windows as .NET. Through the Mono project, this runtime is widely available on
almost all operating systems. However, the specific way that you invoke
<filename>phonix</filename> will depend slightly on your setup.</para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are using any version of Windows and <filename>phonix.exe</filename> is in the
current directory or any directory in <literal>%PATH%</literal>, then you can simply call
<filename>phonix</filename> or <filename>phonix.exe</filename>. Phonix requires .NET Framework 2.0 or
later, which is standard on all recent versions of Windows.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are using Linux, you can invoke Phonix with <literal>./phonix.exe</literal>,
provided that you have the Mono runtime installed. If you are building from
source, there is a <literal>make install</literal> target that will install a <filename>phonix</filename>
script without the <literal>.exe</literal> extension in <literal>/usr/local/bin</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you are using Mac OSX or a POSIX system other than Linux, you can
invoke Phonix with <literal>mono phonix.exe</literal>. You must have the Mono runtime
installed, and you need to explicitly call <literal>mono</literal> in order to run Phonix.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </chapter>

  <chapter label="3" id="The-Phonix-Language">
    <title>The Phonix Language</title>
    <para>This section covers the syntax and meaning of all aspects of a Phonix file in
detail. The Phonix language is simple but powerful, and it should be very easy
for people who are familiar with basic phonological concepts and rule notation.
If you are not familiar with the basics of generative phonology, you may find
this section tough going.</para>
    <para>The Phonix language is <firstterm>declarative</firstterm>: you use Phonix to create a
description of your phonology, and <literal>phonix</literal> reads your description and
applies the rules contained therein to the lexicon. There are three fundamental
elements to a Phonix file: <firstterm>features</firstterm>, <firstterm>symbols</firstterm>, and <firstterm>rules</firstterm>. Each
of these is built up from the previous parts: features are the most basic
element, symbols are composed of features, and rules are composed from symbols
and feature matrices.</para>

    <sect1 label="3.1" id="Features">
      <title>Features</title>
      <para>Phonological features are the contrastive elements that compose the phonemes in
a phonology. Features must be declared before they can be used in symbols or
rules.</para>

      <sect2 label="3.1.1" id="Basic-Features">
        <title>Basic Features</title>
        <para>The simplest feature declaration looks like this:</para>
        <screen>
feature <replaceable>feature-name</replaceable>
</screen>
        <para>The name of a feature can generally be anything, so long as it doesn't contain
spaces or characters with a special meaning in Phonix. For detailed rules, see
<xref linkend="Strings"></xref>. For example:</para>
        <screen>
feature voice
</screen>
        <para>The preceding example creates <literal>voice</literal> as a <firstterm>binary feature</firstterm>, meaning
that it may have the values <literal>+voice</literal> and <literal>-voice</literal>. (There is also a
third value <literal>*voice</literal> which will be talked about shortly.) Phonix supports
three types of features: <firstterm>unary</firstterm>, <firstterm>binary</firstterm>, and <firstterm>scalar</firstterm>. By
default all features are binary. To declare a feature of a different type, you
must use the extended syntax:</para>
        <screen>
feature <replaceable>feature-name</replaceable> (<replaceable>parameter-name</replaceable>=<replaceable>parameter-value</replaceable>)
</screen>
        <para>Note that the parentheses around the parameter list are part of the syntax and
cannot be omitted. Currently the only parameters allowed on feature
declarations are <literal>type</literal>, which may have the values <literal>unary</literal>,
<literal>binary</literal>, <literal>scalar</literal>, or <literal>node</literal>, and <literal>children</literal>, which is
discussed under <xref linkend="Node-Features"></xref>.</para>
        <para>These feature types are discussed in detail in the following sections.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.1.2" id="Unary-Features">
        <title>Unary Features</title>
        <para>The following example declares a unary feature &lsquo;<literal>un</literal>&rsquo;:</para>
        <screen>
feature un (type=unary)
</screen>
        <para>Unary features are either <firstterm>present</firstterm> or <firstterm>absent</firstterm>. A unary feature which
is present is written with the feature name and no other decoration: <literal>un</literal>.
A unary feature which is absent is preceded by &lsquo;<literal>*</literal>&rsquo;: <literal>*un</literal>.</para>
        <para>Unary features are also called "privative features" in linguistic literature.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.1.3" id="Binary-Features">
        <title>Binary Features</title>
        <para>The following example declares a binary feature &lsquo;<literal>bn</literal>&rsquo;:</para>
        <screen>
feature bn (type=binary)
</screen>
        <para>Binary features have both <firstterm>positive</firstterm> and <firstterm>negative</firstterm> values, written as
<literal>+bn</literal> and <literal>-bn</literal> respectively. Additionally, a binary feature may be
<firstterm>absent</firstterm>, which is written the same way as for unary features: <literal>*bn</literal>.
For example, the features &lsquo;<literal>anterior</literal>&rsquo; and &lsquo;<literal>distributed</literal>&rsquo; are not
meaningful for labials, so a labial segment would have the value
<literal>*anterior</literal>.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.1.4" id="Scalar-Features">
        <title>Scalar Features</title>
        <para>The following example declares a scalar feature:</para>
        <screen>
feature sc (type=scalar)
</screen>
        <para>Scalar features may have any non-negative integer value, and are written as
<literal>sc=<replaceable>value</replaceable></literal>. For example, <literal>sc=0</literal>, <literal>sc=1</literal>, and
<literal>sc=123456789</literal> are all valid scalar feature values. However, negative
values such as <literal>sc=-1</literal> and strings such as <literal>sc=foo</literal> are not valid.
Scalar features may also be absent, in which case they are written <literal>*sc</literal>.</para>
        <para>Scalar features may take two additional parameters <literal>min</literal> and <literal>max</literal> to
specify the minimum and maximum value for the feature, as in the following
example:</para>
        <screen>
feature sc (type=scalar min=1 max=5)
</screen>
        <para>Note that if you specify either <literal>min</literal> or <literal>max</literal>, you must specify
both.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.1.5" id="Node-Features">
        <title>Node Features</title>
        <para>Node features are used to represent <emphasis>feature trees</emphasis>, which are used  in
many phonological models. A node feature represents a collection of child
features, and the value of a node feature is the set of values of all of its
children.</para>
        <para>A node feature is declared with the parameter <literal>type=node</literal> and the
<literal>children</literal> parameter. For example:</para>
        <screen>
feature nd (type=node children=a,b,c)
</screen>
        <para>The <literal>children</literal> parameter is required for node features, and forbidden on
all other feature types. Its value is a list of the child features, separated
by commas. You cannot put spaces after the commas unless you put the whole list
in quotes, i.e. either <literal>children=a,b,c</literal> or <literal>children="a, b, c"</literal>. The
features that are named as children must be declared before you declare the
node feature.</para>
        <para>Feature nodes can have any kind of feature as a child, including other nodes.
This allows you to create a multi-level hierarchies. For an example of such a
feature tree, see <xref linkend="@code{std.features}"></xref>.</para>
        <para>Feature nodes are <firstterm>present</firstterm> if any of their child features are present
(i.e. if any child feature has a value other than <literal>*feature</literal>), otherwise
they are <firstterm>absent</firstterm>. Feature nodes are written the same way as unary
features, so that <literal>nd</literal> indicates that a node is present and <literal>*nd</literal>
that it is absent. Note that there are some restrictions on where you can use
node feature values:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Node feature values can't be used at all in symbol declarations. Symbols
can only contain non-node features.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Node feature values that test for the presence of a node (such as
<literal>nd</literal>) can only be used in the <firstterm>match</firstterm> and <firstterm>context</firstterm> portions of a
rule. This is because it isn't meaningful to assign a "present" value directly
to a node.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Node feature values that test for the absence of a node (such as
<literal>*nd</literal>) can be used anywhere within a rule. Assigning a null value to a
node within a rule implies assigning a null value to all children of that node.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 label="3.2" id="Feature-Matrices">
      <title>Feature Matrices</title>
      <para>A <firstterm>feature matrix</firstterm> is a set of features and their values, enclosed in
&lsquo;<literal>[]</literal>&rsquo;. The following line represents a feature matrix.</para>
      <screen>
[+cons -son -cont -str -vc -ro]
</screen>
      <para>Features that are present in your phonology but which are not listed in a
feature matrix are assumed to have the <firstterm>absent</firstterm> value. In the feature
matrix above, the vocalic feature <literal>fr</literal> (front) is unspecified, so it has
the default value of <literal>[*fr]</literal>.</para>
      <para>Feature matrices are used to define symbols and rules. However, only unary,
binary, and scalar feature values can appear in symbols. Node feature values
and variable feature values cannot be used in symbol declarations.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 label="3.3" id="Symbols">
      <title>Symbols</title>
      <para>A <firstterm>symbol</firstterm> in Phonix is a string of text that corresponds to a given
feature matrix.</para>
      <para>Symbols in Phonix are used for three things:</para>
      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>To define the phonetic symbols represented by the strings in your lexicon
files.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To provide a convenient shortcut for writing rules that refer to specific
phonemes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To define the strings used to represent feature matrices in output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <sect2 label="3.3.1" id="Basic-Symbols">
        <title>Basic symbols</title>
        <para>A basic symbol declaration looks like this:</para>
        <screen>
symbol <replaceable>symbol-string</replaceable> <replaceable>feature-matrix</replaceable>
</screen>
        <para>For example, this is the declaration of the symbol &lsquo;<literal>s</literal>&rsquo; in the standard
symbol set:</para>
        <screen>
symbol s [+cons -son +cont +str -vc +ant -dist]
</screen>
        <para>Having this symbol declaration does three things:</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <para>Allows you to use the string <literal>s</literal> in your input to Phonix.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Allows you to use <literal>s</literal> as a shorthand for <literal>[+cons -son +cont
+str -vc +ant -dist]</literal> in your rules.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Causes the feature matrix <literal>[+cons -son +cont +str -vc +ant -dist]</literal>
to be translated to <literal>s</literal> in phonix output.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Every character you use in in your lexicon file must be defined as a symbol, or
else Phonix will quit with an error message. If your rules result in an output
feature matrix for which there is no symbol, Phonix will print a warning and
insert the dummy symbol <literal>[?]</literal> as a placeholder in your output.</para>
        <para>Any Unicode character that doesn't have a special meaning in Phonix can be used
as a symbol. So if you want to define â˜ƒ (Unicode snowman) as a symbol in your
phonology, you're welcome to do so.</para>
        <para>Symbols can have any number of characters in them. Phonix always maps input
strings to the longest matching symbol, however. For example, say you define
the following symbols:</para>
        <screen>
symbol s  [...]
symbol k  [...]
symbol sk [...]
</screen>
        <para>If your input or rules contain the characters &lsquo;<literal>sk</literal>&rsquo;, these will be mapped
to the symbol /sk/, and not to the sequence /s/+/k/.</para>
        <para>For many examples of symbol definitions, see <xref linkend="@code{std.symbols}"></xref>.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.3.2" id="Diacritic-Symbols">
        <title>Diacritic Symbols</title>
        <para>Phonix allows you to define certain symbols as <firstterm>diacritics</firstterm>, which are
modifiers applied to other symbols. Diacritics are defined like this:</para>
        <screen>
symbol <replaceable>diacritic-string</replaceable> (diacritic) <replaceable>feature-matrix</replaceable>
</screen>
        <para>For example, the following is the declaration of the nasality diacritic in the
standard diacritic set:</para>
        <screen>
symbol ~ (diacritic) [+nas]
</screen>
        <para>Diacritics differ from basic symbols in several ways:</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <para>A diacritic is not a segment of its own, but rather adds its features to
the symbol that it modifies. Take the symbol /s/ defined above, together with
the nasality diacritic /~/. The combination of these symbols /s~/ results in a
single feature matrix with the features <literal>[+cons -son +cont +str -vc +ant
-dist +nas]</literal>. These are the feature values for /s/, with the <literal>+nas</literal> value
of /~/ added to them.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Diacritics must follow a base symbol in your input. If /s/ is a base
symbol and /~/ is a diacritic, then <literal>s</literal> is a valid input string, as is
<literal>s~</literal>.  However, <literal>~</literal> and <literal>~s</literal> are not valid input. Phonix will
quit with an error if it encounters such a string.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>When representing the output of your rules with symbols, Phonix will
first look for a base symbol that matches the output feature matrix. It then
adds diacritics as necessary. Phonix will try to find the fewest number of
diacritics necessary to represent your output.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>For many examples of diacritic definitions, see
<xref linkend="@code{std.symbols.diacritics}"></xref>.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 label="3.4" id="Rules">
      <title>Rules</title>
      <para>The <firstterm>rule</firstterm> is the most complex and the most variable object in Phonix. A
rule describes the conditions under which one phonological unit is transformed
into another.</para>

      <sect2 label="3.4.1" id="Parts-of-a-rule">
        <title>Parts of a rule</title>
        <para>A complete rule has the following syntax:</para>
        <screen>
rule <replaceable>name</replaceable> (<replaceable>parameters</replaceable>) <replaceable>match</replaceable> =&gt; <replaceable>action</replaceable> / <replaceable>context</replaceable> // <replaceable>excluded-context</replaceable>
</screen>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <firstterm>name</firstterm> of the rule can be any Phonix string. See <xref linkend="Strings"></xref>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <firstterm>parameters</firstterm> are optional and define characteristics of how the
rule is applied. If you don't apply any parameters, you can omit the
parentheses.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <firstterm>match</firstterm> is a sequence of feature matrices or symbols that matches
the segments that the transformation works on.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <firstterm>action</firstterm> is sequence of feature matrices or symbols that defines
the transformations applied to the match.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <firstterm>context</firstterm> defines the conditions under which the transformation
occurs. These are the adjacent segments which aren't themselves altered, but
which are required to trigger the rule. If the rule is <firstterm>unconditional</firstterm> and
does not depend on the surrounding segments, you can omit the context and the
excluded context.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <firstterm>excluded-context</firstterm> defines conditions under which the rule should
not apply. These are exceptions to the conditions in the context.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>These are described in more detail in the following sections.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.4.2" id="Basic-transformations">
        <title>Basic transformations</title>
        <para>The simplest transformation is one that has no context or parameters and acts
only on a single phoneme, as in the following example.</para>
        <screen>
rule s-to-z
    s =&gt; z
</screen>
        <para>The <firstterm>match</firstterm> here is the segment /s/, and the <firstterm>action</firstterm> is to turn all
such segments into /z/. Since /s/ and /z/ differ only by voice, we can also
write this rule like this (using the appreviation <literal>vc</literal> for voice, as in
the standard feature set):</para>
        <screen>
rule s-voicing
    s =&gt; [+vc]
</screen>
        <para>Here the action is a feature matrix rather than a segment. The effect of this
is to take whichever value for <literal>voice</literal> the input previously had and
replace it with <literal>+voice</literal>. You can also use a feature matrix in the match
portion of the rule to match against a class of segments:</para>
        <screen>
rule continuant-voicing
    [+cont] =&gt; [+vc]
</screen>
        <para>The matrix <literal>[+cont]</literal> causes this rule to match all segments that have the
feature <literal>+cont</literal>, and applies the feature <literal>+vc</literal> to them.</para>
        <para>Most rules do not apply everywhere, however, but have some <firstterm>context</firstterm>. The
context in Phonix consists of, at minimum, the character <literal>_</literal> with any
number of feature matrices or symbols before or after it. The <literal>_</literal>
character stands for the segment(s) of the match/action. Regardless of how many
segments are matched or transformed, you must write only one underscore. For
example, let's modify our previous rule to only apply after a nasal:</para>
        <screen>
rule postnasal-voicing
    [+cont] =&gt; [+vc] / [+nas] _
</screen>
        <para>In this case, the context <literal>/ [+nas] _</literal> indicates that the segments matched
must be preceded by a segment with the feature <literal>+nas</literal>.</para>
        <para>To indicate word boundaries we use <literal>$</literal>. The <literal>$</literal> character can stand
for either the beginning or the end of a word. It can only appear as the first
or the last character of the rule context (or both), but it cannot appear
internal to a rule. Suppose that we wish to further restrict our rule to only
apply at the end of a word. In this case, we write this:</para>
        <screen>
rule final-postnasal-voicing
    [+cont] =&gt; [+vc] / [+nas] _ $
</screen>
        <para>If we wish to add an exception to this rule, we use the <emphasis>excluded
context</emphasis>. This is indicated by a double-slash <literal>//</literal> after the context. If
the rule includes an excluded context, then phonix will check both that the
context matches the input and that the excluded context does <emphasis>not</emphasis> match.
For example:</para>
        <screen>
rule postnasal-voicing-with-exception
    [+cont] =&gt; [+vc] / [+nas] _ // N _
</screen>
        <para>Here we voice continuants after nasals, <emphasis>except</emphasis> after /N/ (the velar
nasal).</para>
        <para>If you wish, you can also indicate the excluded context without the context:</para>
        <screen>
rule voicing-with-exception
    [+cont] =&gt; [+vc] // $ _
</screen>
        <para>This voices all continuants unless they are the first segment in the word. Note
that we could accomplish the exact same thing with:</para>
        <screen>
rule voicing-with-exception
    [+cont] =&gt; [+vc] / [] _
</screen>
        <para>Here, we specify that voicing occurs when the continuant is preceded by any
segment. (A feature matrix with no values, indicated by <literal>[]</literal>, acts as a
match for any segment.) This illustrates that an excluded context can usually
be indicated by a properly constructed matching context and vice-versa.  The
excluded context construct is provided only to make rules clearer and easier to
understand.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.4.3" id="Inserting-and-deleting">
        <title>Inserting and deleting</title>
        <para>Insertion and deletion rules are written with the help of the special character
<literal>*</literal>, which you should think of as "nothing". To write an insertion rule,
specify that "nothing" becomes something:</para>
        <screen>
rule e-epenthesis
    * =&gt; e / $ _ s[-cont]
</screen>
        <para>This is a familiar rule found in many Romance languages, which adds an
epenthetic /e/ following an initial cluster with /s/.</para>
        <para>The opposite of insertion is deletion, in which something becomes nothing.
E.g.:</para>
        <screen>
rule final-cons-deletion
    [-son] =&gt; * / _ $
</screen>
        <para>Here, the "something" is any non-sonorant (<literal>-son</literal>), which becomes
"nothing" when followed by the word boundary.</para>
        <para>Our nothing character is important when writing rules in which multiple
segments become one. For example, to express that /s/+/k/ becomes /S/, you
<emphasis>cannot</emphasis> write the following:</para>
        <screen>
# DOES NOT WORK - Phonix will not compile this rule
rule sk-coalescence
    sk =&gt; S
</screen>
        <para>The problem with this is that you must have the same number of segments both
before and after the <literal>=&gt;</literal> symbol. To accomplish what you want, just
specify that one of the input segments is deleted:</para>
        <screen>
rule sk-coalescence
    sk =&gt; S*
</screen>
        <para>This rule will compile and function as expected.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.4.4" id="Rule-variables">
        <title>Rule variables</title>
        <para>It is common for linguistic rules to operate when two segments share the same
value for some feature, regardless of what the particular value of that feature
is. The linguistic literature traditionally indicates such values with Greek
letters to represent the variables. Phonix allows you to indicate such rules
without the Greek using <firstterm>variable feature values</firstterm>, which are indicated by
<literal>$</literal> preceding a feature name.</para>
        <para>Consider the following rule:</para>
        <screen>
rule cluster-spirantization
    [$vc -son] =&gt; [+cont] / _ [$vc -son]
</screen>
        <para>This rule in English reads as "spirantize any non-sonorant when followed by
another non-sonorant of the same voicing". The feature values <literal>-son</literal> and
<literal>+cont</literal> are ordinary feature values. The feature value <literal>$vc</literal> is
different: it doesn't stipulate <literal>+vc</literal> or <literal>-vc</literal>, but rather requires
that the value for <literal>vc</literal> be the same in both the match and context
segments. This rule will change <literal>apta</literal> into <literal>afta</literal> since both /p/ and
/t/ have the same voicinge, and it will change <literal>abda</literal> into <literal>avda</literal>
since /b/ and /d/ have the some voicing. However, it won't change <literal>abta</literal>
at all, because the segments in that word are of different voicing.</para>
        <para>Variables may also occur in rule actions. The following illustrates a nasal
assimilation rule:</para>
        <screen>
rule nasal-assimilate
    [-cont] =&gt; [$nas $son] / _ [-cont $nas $son]
</screen>
        <para>This rule reads as "any non-continuant takes the nasality and sonority of a
following non-contiuant segment". The values <literal>$nas $son</literal> in the rule
action have the effect of setting <literal>nas</literal> and <literal>son</literal> in the matched
segment to whatever value they have in the context segment. This will cause,
for example /d/+/m/ to become /n/+/m/, while /n/+/b/ becomes /d/+/b/.</para>
        <para>In order for a variable feature value to be meaningful, it has to occur at
least twice in a rule. Consider the following modified example:</para>
        <screen>
rule nasal-assimilate-mod
    [-cont] =&gt; [$nas] / _ [-cont $nas $son]
</screen>
        <para>This rule parses and executes without any warning, but the value <literal>$son</literal> in
the rule context has no effect, since there is no other instance of <literal>$son</literal>
to match against.</para>
        <para>The following example, however, will generate a warning message:</para>
        <screen>
rule nasal-assimilate-mod2
    [-cont] =&gt; [$nas $son] / _ [-cont $nas]
</screen>
        <para>In this case we are trying to set the value of <literal>son</literal> in the rule action,
but the value for <literal>son</literal> is not defined anywhere else in the rule. Since
this usually indicates a mistake, Phonix issues a warning and leaves the value
of <literal>son</literal> unchanged.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.4.5" id="Node-feature-values">
        <title>Node feature values</title>
        <para>Node features are features with one or more child features (see <xref linkend="Node-Features"></xref>), and they have some special properties.</para>
        <para>A node feature is <firstterm>present</firstterm> if one or more of its children is present. Node
features don't have any value of their own. Within a rule you can use the same
syntax that is used for unary values to test for the presence of a node:</para>
        <screen>
rule postlabial-centralization
    [+fr -bk] =&gt; [-fr] / [Labial] _
</screen>
        <para>In this case we are testing for the presence of the <literal>Labial</literal> node. This is
especially convenient because it allows us to capture both <literal>+ro</literal> segments
(rounded vowels) and <literal>-ro</literal> segments (labial consonants), which otherwise
can't be represented in a natural class.</para>
        <para>Conversely, you can test for the absence of a particular node by preceding the
node name with <literal>*</literal>, as with other features. For example, the following
rule centralizes vowels after non-<literal>Coronal</literal> segments.</para>
        <screen>
rule nonlabial-centralization
    [+fr -bk] =&gt; [-fr] / [*Coronal] _
</screen>
        <para>This rule will apply whenever the action segment is preceded by something that
has no non-null values for features that occur under the <literal>Coronal</literal> node.
You could also write <literal>[*Coronal]</literal> as <literal>[*ant *dist]</literal>, since <literal>ant</literal>
and <literal>dist</literal> are the only two features under <literal>Coronal</literal>. These two forms
have exactly the same meaning, though the former is clearer and easier to
understand.</para>
        <para>Within the action portion of a rule, you can use this syntax to set an entire
group of segments to their absent values. For example, the following rule
reduces all stops in final position to /?/ by removing every feature under the
<literal>Place</literal> node.</para>
        <screen>
rule final-glottalization
    [-cont] =&gt; [*Place] / _ $
</screen>
        <para>As this rule illustrates, you may use the <literal>*Node</literal> syntax in a rule action,
but you cannot use the <literal>Node</literal> syntax in an action, because it makes no
sense to assign a value directly to a node.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.4.6" id="Assimilation-and-gemination">
        <title>Assimilation and gemination</title>
        <para>Node features (see <xref linkend="Node-Features"></xref>) are especially useful for assimilation
and gemination rules, as we'll see.</para>
        <para>A common phonological process is <emphasis>nasal place assimilation</emphasis>, by which
nasals in coda positions take on the place of the following segments. These
rules can be written with a flat feature set by writing a complex rule that
assigns every feature value correspending to the notion of "place". However,
this can get very cumbersome&ndash;consider that to write a <emphasis>total</emphasis>
assimilation rule, you would need include every single feature as a variable!</para>
        <para>However, these processes are considerably simplified by using node features.
For example, using <xref linkend="@code{std.features}"></xref>, we can write a nasal place
assimilation rule as follows:</para>
        <screen>
rule nasal-place-assimilation
    [+nas] =&gt; [$Place] / _ [+cons $Place]
</screen>
        <para>This rule is greatly simplified by using the <literal>Place</literal> node, which has as
its children all of the features that contribute to place of articulation. The
effect of the <literal>$Place</literal> variable is the same as any other rule variable: it
copies the value of <literal>Place</literal> from the context to the action segment.
However, because <literal>Place</literal> is a node, every single feature value under
<literal>Place</literal> in the feature hierarchy is copied as well.</para>
        <para>You can extend this even further for a gemination rule that duplicates
<emphasis>all</emphasis> of the features for a given segment:</para>
        <screen>
rule intervocalic-gemination
    * =&gt; [$ROOT] / [-cons][+cons $ROOT] _ [-cons]
</screen>
        <para>Here a consonantal segment is doubled when surrounded on either side by
non-consonantal segments. The feature <literal>ROOT</literal> has as its children every
feature in <literal><literal>std.features</literal></literal>, and so the inserted segment copies every
value from the preceding segment.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.4.7" id="Scalar-feature-value-operators">
        <title>Scalar feature value operators</title>
        <para>There a few special operators that can be used with scalar feature values to
perform integer operations and comparisons. Scalar feature values are unlike
other feature value types in that they represent a range of integer values, and
so it's often useful to perform simple numeric operations on them.</para>

        <sect3 label="3.4.7.1">
          <title>Comparison operators</title>
          <para>Scalar comparison operators can be used anywhere within a feature matrix that
does matching, i.e. in the match portion of the rule, or to the left of the
arrow in the action. The most basic scalar comparison is for equality, which
has the same format as a regular scalar value:</para>
          <screen>
[sc=2]
</screen>
          <para>This feature matrix will match any segment for which the scalar feature
<literal>sc</literal> has the value <literal>2</literal>.</para>
          <para>You can also check for <firstterm>inequality</firstterm> with <literal>&lt;&gt;</literal>:</para>
          <screen>
[sc&lt;&gt;2]
</screen>
          <para>This matrix will match any segment which has a value for <literal>sc</literal> other than
<literal>2</literal>. This includes values like <literal>sc=3</literal>, <literal>sc=1</literal>, and even null
values like <literal>*sc</literal>.</para>
          <para>There are also operators for <firstterm>greater than</firstterm>, <firstterm>greater than or equal</firstterm>,
<firstterm>less than</firstterm>, and <firstterm>less than or equal</firstterm>, which have the familiar numeric
notation:</para>
          <screen>
sc&gt;2    # matches sc=3, sc=4, etc.
sc&gt;=2   # matches sc=2, sc=3, etc.
sc&lt;2    # matches sc=1, sc=0
sc&lt;=2   # matches sc=2, sc=1, sc=0
</screen>
          <para>These numeric comparison operators will only match if the segment they're
matching against has a defined value for <literal>sc</literal>. They will always return
false when comparing against <literal>*sc</literal>.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 label="3.4.7.2">
          <title>Addition and subtraction operators</title>
          <para>You can use addition and subtraction operators to add to or subtract from a
scalar feature value. These operators can only be used in a rule action, on the
right-hand side of the arrow.</para>
          <para>The <literal>=+</literal> operator is used to add to a scalar feature value. (Note that the
equal sign comes first, unlike most programming languages.)</para>
          <screen>
rule add-two
    [sc&gt;0] =&gt; [sc=+2]
</screen>
          <para>This rule matches any segment that has a value for <literal>sc</literal> greater than zero,
and adds two to that value. An input segment with <literal>sc=1</literal> would have
<literal>sc=3</literal> after this rule applied.</para>
          <para>The subtraction operator <literal>=-</literal> works much the same way:</para>
          <screen>
rule subtract-one
    [sc&gt;2] =&gt; [sc=-1]
</screen>
          <para>This rule matches any segment that has a value for <literal>sc</literal> greater than two,
and subtracts one from that value. An input segment with <literal>sc=3</literal> would have
<literal>sc=2</literal> after this rule applied.</para>
          <para>These operators may generate non-fatal warnings under a few conditions:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the scalar feature value is null (e.g. <literal>*sc</literal>) and you attempt to
apply the addition or subtraction operator, Phonix will issue a warning and
leave the value unchanged.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>If the scalar feature has a minimum and a maximum (see <xref linkend="Scalar-Features"></xref>) and applying the addition or subtraction operator causes the scalar
to go out of range, Phonix will also issue a warning and leave the value
unchanged.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.4.8" id="Optional-and-repeated-segments">
        <title>Optional and repeated segments</title>
        <para>You often need to make some segments in your rule <emphasis>optional</emphasis>. In
traditional linguistic notation, this is indicated by enclosing the optional
segment(s) in parenthesis, and the same convention is followed by Phonix.</para>
        <screen>
rule optional-r
    a =&gt; i / k(r) _
</screen>
        <para>This rule will take the sequences /ka/ and /kra/ and convert them to /ki/ and
/kri/ respectively. The <literal>(r)</literal> in the rule context indicates that the /r/
optionally follows the /k/.</para>
        <para>This syntax can be extended to indicate that a segment is repeated <emphasis>zero
or more times</emphasis> or <emphasis>one or more times</emphasis>. These are indicated by using the
operators <literal>*</literal> or <literal>+</literal> respectively, together with the parentheses.</para>
        <para>The operator <literal>*</literal> following a parenthesized segment indicates that the
segment may appear zero or more times.</para>
        <screen>
rule multiple-r
    a =&gt; i / k(r)* _
</screen>
        <para>This rule will match against /ka/ and /kra/, as the one above, but it also
matches /krra/ or /krrrrrrrrrra/ or any number of other repetitions of /r/.</para>
        <para>The operator <literal>+</literal> following a parenthesized segment indicates that the
segment may appear one or more times.</para>
        <screen>
rule at-least-one-r
    a =&gt; i / k(r)+ _
</screen>
        <para>This rule, unlike the ones above, does <emphasis>not</emphasis> match /ka/. It does, however,
match /kra/, /krra/, and any other input with at least one /r/.</para>

        <sect3 label="3.4.8.1">
          <title>Differences from regular expressions</title>
          <para>The <literal>*</literal> and <literal>+</literal> operators are similar to the equivalent regular
expression operators. However, Phonix is <emphasis>not</emphasis> a regular expression
engine, and there are important differences between regular expressions and the
Phonix engine.</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The parentheses around segment(s) preceding the <literal>*</literal> or <literal>+</literal> are
not optional.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Phonix does not do <firstterm>backtracking</firstterm>, so a rule context involving
multiple <literal>*</literal> or <literal>+</literal> expressions may not work as expected.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Phonix matches are always greedy (taking in as many segments as they
can). There are no non-greedy match operators in Phonix.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Many rules using multiple match segments can be expressed more succinctly by
using a filter instead. See <xref linkend="@code{filter}"></xref>.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.4.9" id="Rule-parameters">
        <title>Rule parameters</title>
        <para>Rule parameters alter the execution of your rule in some way that can't be
indicated in the rule itself. Parameters take the form
<literal><replaceable>param-name</replaceable>=<replaceable>param-value</replaceable></literal>, and are enclosed in parentheses
after the rule name, with spaces between them if there are more than one. The
following rule example specifies the <literal>direction</literal> and <literal>filter</literal>
parameters:</para>
        <screen>
rule leftward-example (direction=right-to-left filter=[+cons]) s =&gt; z
</screen>
        <para>There are two different parameters given in this example:
<literal>direction=left-to-right</literal> and <literal>filter=[+cons]</literal>. Note that the
parameters are separated by a space, not by a comma.</para>
        <para>Supported rule parameters are discussed below.</para>

        <sect3 label="3.4.9.1" id="@code{direction}">
          <title><literal>direction</literal></title>
          <para>The <literal>direction</literal> parameter defines the direction in which the rule scans
for matching contexts. This can be important if one application of a rule may
create the context for further applications. To specify the direction for a
rule, specify the parameter <literal>direction=<replaceable>direction-value</replaceable></literal>. Valid
direction values are <literal>left-to-right</literal> and <literal>right-to-left</literal>, with
<literal>left-to-right</literal> as the default.</para>
          <para>A good example for a direction-sensitive rule is voice agreement. Suppose we
have a rule that all consonants in a cluster must agree with the voice of the
last consonant. The following rule does not accomplish that:</para>
          <screen>
# This doesn't work as expected
rule voicing-agreement
    [+cons] =&gt; [+vc] / _ [+cons +vc]
</screen>
          <para>Given an input word like <literal>astga</literal>, the output of this rule will be
<literal>asdga</literal>&mdash;only the middle consonant in the cluster is affected! This is
because the default rule direction is to the right. First the /s/ is evaluated,
but this /s/ is followed by /t/, so the rule does not apply. Then /t/ followed
by /g/ is evaluated. This does match the required context, so /t/ becomes /d/.
However, the /s/ is never reevaluated, leaving <literal>asdga</literal> as the result. To
fix this, specify that the rule applies from the right to the left:</para>
          <screen>
rule voicing-agreement (direction=right-to-left)
    [+cons] =&gt; [+vc] / _ [+cons +vc]
</screen>
          <para>This rule will transform <literal>astga</literal> into <literal>azdga</literal> as expected. First /t/
followed by /g/ is evaluated, transforming the /t/ into /d/. Then /s/ followed
by /d/ is evaluated, and the /s/ becomes /z/.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 label="3.4.9.2" id="@code{filter}">
          <title><literal>filter</literal></title>
          <para>Rule filters are a powerful way to express rules that only apply to certain
classes of segments and ignore intervening segments. A familiar real-world
example of this kind of rule is <emphasis>vowel harmony</emphasis>, which typically works on
vowels regardless of intervening consonants. To add a filter to a rule, specify
the parameter <literal>filter=<replaceable>filter-value</replaceable></literal>, where the <firstterm>filter-value</firstterm>
may be a feature matrix or a symbol.</para>
          <para>When you apply a filter, the rule acts as if those segments not matching the
filter were not present at all in the input. Take the following vowel harmony
rule:</para>
          <screen>
rule vowel-harmony (filter=[+syll])
    [-fr] =&gt; [+fr -bk] / _ [+fr]
</screen>
          <para>This rule turns back vowels into front vowels when followed by other front
vowels, and will work correctly regardless of how many non-vowel segments
intervene between the vowels. The filter <literal>[+syll]</literal> effectively removes all
non-syllabic constants from the input for the duration of the rule. Therefore,
the context of the rule is written as if the front vowel that triggers vowel
harmony immediately follows the matching vowel.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 label="3.4.9.3" id="@code{persist}">
          <title><literal>persist</literal></title>
          <para>A <firstterm>persistent rule</firstterm> is a rule that applies at all stages of the phonology,
rather than at a specific point in the derivation of the output form.
Persistent rules in Phonix are indicated with the rule parameter
<literal>persist</literal>, which does not take any value. The usual purpose of a
persistent rule is to ensure that redundant features values are maintained. For
example, in most languages all segments that are <literal>+syll</literal> are also
<literal>+vc</literal>. If we wanted to enforce this redundancy, we could do so with the
following persistent rule:</para>
          <screen>
rule voiced-syllabics (persist)
    [+syll] =&gt; [+vc]
</screen>
          <para>Of course, this rule only serves some purpose if there are other processes
which might make a voiceless segment syllabic.</para>
          <para>Persistent rules are applied once at the start of rule application, and
thereafter every time that some other rule changes the input. This is true
regardless of where in your Phonix file the persistent rule is
defined&ndash;persistent rules ignore normal rule ordering. However, the ordering of
persistent rules relative to each other is maintained.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 label="3.4.9.4" id="@code{applicationRate}">
          <title><literal>applicationRate</literal></title>
          <para>A <firstterm>sporadic rule</firstterm> is a rule which does not apply to every word in the input
lexicon, but rather applies randomly to some words and not others. Phonix
allows you to create this kind of rule with the rule parameter
<literal>applicationRate=<replaceable>ratio</replaceable></literal>. The <replaceable>ratio</replaceable> parameter to
<literal>applicationRate</literal> must be a decimal between 0 and 1. Examples:</para>
          <screen>
# This rule deletes /b/ 25% of the time
rule sometimes-delete (applicationRate=0.25) b =&gt; *

# With applicationRate=1, the rule applies 100% of the time. This is
# equivalent to omitting the applicationRate parameter entirely.
rule always-delete (applicationRate=1) a =&gt; *

# With applictionRate=0, the rule applies 0% of the time. This is
# equivalent to leaving the rule out.
rule never-delete (applicationRate=0) c =&gt; *
</screen>
          <para>Setting the value for <literal>applicationRate</literal> to less than 0 or more than 1 will
cause Phonix to print an error message and quit.</para>
          <para>Note that if you create sporadic rules in this fashion, Phonix's output will no
longer be predictable or consistent from run to run. There is no way to ensure
that a sporadic rule will always apply to given word, nor can you predict which
words will be affected by which rules in any given invocation.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 label="3.5" id="Syllables">
      <title>Syllables</title>
      <para>Many languages use syllables as an important phonological unit. For this reason
Phonix provides special syntax both for dividing input words into syllables
with syllable templates and for creating phonological rules that depend on
syllable structure.</para>

      <sect2 label="3.5.1" id="Syllable-templates">
        <title>Syllable templates</title>
        <para>The <literal>syllable</literal> declaration is used to describe the valid templates that
are used for syllabification. The form of the syllable template is:</para>
        <screen>
syllable
    onset <replaceable>onset-segments</replaceable>
    nucleus <replaceable>nucleus-segments</replaceable>
    coda <replaceable>coda-segments</replaceable>
</screen>
        <para>The entries <replaceable>onset-segments</replaceable>, <replaceable>nucleus-segments</replaceable>, <replaceable>coda-segments</replaceable>
are sequences of segments (feature matrices or symbols) as used in the match
portion of a rule. These define the segments that are allowed at every position
in the syllable. As a full example, consider the following:</para>
        <screen>
syllable onset [+cons] nucleus [-cons +son] coda [+son]
</screen>
        <para>This allows any <literal>[+cons]</literal> segment in syllable onsets, any <literal>[-cons
+son]</literal> segment as a nucleus, and only <literal>[+son]</literal> segments as the coda.  This
creates (C)V(C) syllables, since onsets and codas are optional by default. Onset
clusters and coda clusters are not allowed by this template, since only one
segment is allowed in the onset.</para>
        <para>If we wanted to allow an optional liquid to follow a stop in the onset cluster,
we could rewrite the syllable template this way:</para>
        <screen>
syllable
    onset [+cons]
    onset [+cons -cont -son][+son +cont]
    nucleus [-cons +son]
    coda [+son]
</screen>
        <para>Here <literal>onset</literal> appears twice, giving two alternate templates for syllable
onsets, one which allows any single <literal>[+cons]</literal> segment, and another which
allows a stop (<literal>[+cons -cont -son]</literal>) followed by a liquid (<literal>[+son
+cont]</literal>). Phonix will attempt to create syllables matching either of the given
templates.</para>
        <para>Any of the syllable parts <literal>onset</literal>, <literal>nucleus</literal>, and <literal>coda</literal> can be
repeated as many times as desired. You can also abbreviate optional segments in
a syllable template with <literal>()</literal>, as in the following example that allows an
optional sonorant to precede a non-sonorant in a syllable coda:</para>
        <screen>
syllable
    onset [+cons]
    nucleus [-cons +son]
    coda ([+son])[+cons -son]
</screen>
        <para>However, <literal>()</literal> is the only regex-like operator that can be used in a
syllable template. The extended operators <literal>()+</literal> and <literal>()*</literal> are not
allowed, and will result in parsing errors.</para>
        <para>To specify that a syllable template should not allow codas (or, more rarely,
allow no onsets), the <literal>coda</literal> or <literal>onset</literal> element should be omitted:</para>
        <screen>
syllable
    onset [+cons]
    nucleus [-cons +son]
</screen>
        <para>This creates (C)V syllables and does not allow codas. The <literal>nucleus</literal>
element may not be omitted.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.5.2" id="Syllable-rules">
        <title>Syllable rules</title>
        <para>A <literal>syllable</literal> template is actually a special kind of rule. All rules,
including syllable rules, apply only once, and apply in the order that they are
declared. This means that:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Not every segment will necessarily be assigned to a syllable if there is
no syllable template that can cover every segment. Phonix does not do anything
with unsyllabified segments by default. If you want to avoid this, you need to
write your own rule to delete, add an epenthetic segment, or otherwise modify
the unsyllabified segments.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The syllabification built by a <literal>syllable</literal> rule persists after the
syllable rule occurs, even if segments are inserted or deleted.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Insertions, deletions, and other phonological modifications do not
automatically trigger resyllabification. This means that an inserted segment is
not automatically added to a syllable, and deleted segments may leave behind
incomplete syllables.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If you want to force a word to be resyllabified after every change, you
may use the <literal>persist</literal> syllable parameter (see <xref linkend="Syllable-parameters"></xref>).
However, since insertions and deletions often accompany changes in the syllable
template, you may want to follow an insertion or deletion rule with a new
<literal>syllable</literal> rule.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>If you use the <literal>-d</literal> or <literal>--debug</literal> flags to <filename>phonix</filename>, then when a
syllable rule applies, the new syllabification of the word is printed. Every
syllable is written inside angle brackets (<literal>&lt;&gt;</literal>), with a double colon (<literal>::</literal>)
between the onset and the nucleus, and a single colon (<literal>:</literal>) between the nucleus
and the coda. For example, the syllabification of hypothetical word like
<literal>abarno</literal> with a (C)V(C) template is presented as:</para>
        <screen>
&lt;a&gt; &lt;b :: a : r&gt; &lt;n : o&gt;
</screen>
        <para>The spacing is used to avoid confusing the syllable separators with the colon
symbol.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.5.3" id="Syllable-parameters">
        <title>Syllable parameters</title>
        <para>Syllable parameters affect the way that the syllable template is evaluated and
the syllable rule is applied. Syllable parameters appear in parenthesis
directly immediately after <literal>syllable</literal>, e.g.:</para>
        <screen>
syllable (<replaceable>parameter-list</replaceable>)
    onset <replaceable>onset-segments</replaceable>
    nucleus <replaceable>nucleus-segments</replaceable>
    coda <replaceable>coda-segments</replaceable>
</screen>
        <sect3 label="3.5.3.1">
          <title><literal>onsetRequired</literal> and <literal>codaRequired</literal></title>
          <para>The parameters <literal>onsetRequired</literal> and <literal>codaRequired</literal> cause the
<literal>onset</literal> and <literal>coda</literal> portions of the syllable template respectively to
be required in all complete syllables. By default the onset and the coda are
optional. Because of this, the following syllable declaration with no
parameters creates (C)V(C) syllables:</para>
          <screen>
syllable
    onset [+cons]
    nucleus [-cons +son]
    coda [+cons]
</screen>
          <para>Given an input string such as <literal>alona</literal>, this rule will present the
syllabification <literal>&lt;a&gt; &lt;l :: o&gt; &lt;n :: a&gt;</literal>, in which the first syllable has
neither onset nor coda, and the remaining syllables have no coda.</para>
          <para>However, we can make onsets obligatory by adding <literal>onsetRequired</literal>:</para>
          <screen>
syllable (onsetRequired)
    onset [+cons]
    nucleus [-cons +son]
    coda [+cons]
</screen>
          <para>Given the input <literal>alona</literal>, this syllabifies <literal>a &lt;l :: o&gt; &lt;n :: a&gt;</literal>,
leaving the initial <literal>a</literal> unsyllabified, since no onset can be found for
that nucleus. Only the latter two syllables are constructed, since only those
syllables can onsets as required.</para>
          <para>Likewise, we can require both onsets and codas:</para>
          <screen>
syllable (onsetRequired codaRequired)
    onset [+cons]
    nucleus [-cons +son]
    coda [+cons]
</screen>
          <para>This will syllabify <literal>alona</literal> as <literal>a &lt;l :: o : n&gt; a</literal>, leaving both the
initial and the final <literal>a</literal> unsyllabified, since the medial <literal>lon</literal> is
the only syllable that can be constructed with both an onset and a coda.</para>
          <para>Finally, in the unusual case that we wish to require codas but not onsets, we
can create the following:</para>
          <screen>
syllable (codaRequired)
    onset [+cons]
    nucleus [-cons +son]
    coda [+cons]
</screen>
          <para>This syllabifies <literal>alona</literal> as <literal>&lt;a : l&gt; &lt;o : n&gt; a</literal>, with the first two
syllables having no onsets, and the final <literal>a</literal> unsyllabified since no coda
can be found for it.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 label="3.5.3.2">
          <title><literal>nucleusPreference</literal></title>
          <para>The <literal>nucleusPreference</literal> parameter controls whether syllable nuclei prefer
to fall to the right or to the left in situations where there is ambiguity as
to where the nucleus should fall. It takes two values, <literal>right</literal> and
<literal>left</literal>. The value <literal>right</literal> is the default.</para>
          <para>This in turn controls whether rising diphthongs or falling diphthongs are
preferred in situations where either one is allowed by the syllable template.
Consider an underlying vowel sequence /ui/ with allophonic rules that allow /u/
to be both [u] and [w], and /i/ to be [i] and [j]. We'll represent this by the
following extremely simplified syllable template:</para>
          <screen>
syllable
    onset []([+son])
    nucleus [-cons +son]
    coda []
</screen>
          <para>This template requires vowels in the nuclear position, but allows anything into
onsets and codas. Onsets may also form clusters with sonorants as the second
element. Given this template, the input string <literal>bui</literal> could be syllabified
as <literal>&lt;bu :: i&gt;</literal> (i.e. [bwi]) or <literal>&lt;b :: u : i&gt;</literal> (i.e. [buj]).</para>
          <para>The default case is to produce <literal>&lt;bu :: i&gt;</literal>, which is equivalent to
<literal>nucleusPreference=right</literal>. To force the nucleus to the left, use
<literal>nucleusPreference=left</literal>:</para>
          <screen>
syllable (nucleusPreference=left)
    onset []([+son])
    nucleus [-cons +son]
    coda []
</screen>
          <para>This template will produce syllables with the nuclei aligned to the left
whenever possible, creating <literal>&lt;b :: u : i&gt;</literal> ([buj]) as the syllabification
of <literal>bui</literal>.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 label="3.5.3.3">
          <title><literal>persist</literal></title>
          <para>The <literal>persist</literal> parameter has the same affect as the <literal>persist</literal>
parameter on rule declarations: it causes the syllabification rule to apply
after every other rule, ensuring that words are automatically resyllabified
after every change.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.5.4" id="Using-syllable-elements-in-rules">
        <title>Using syllable elements in rules</title>
        <para>To write a rule that is triggered by a particular syllable position, you can
include the syllable position inside angle brackets (<literal>&lt;&gt;</literal>) inside a
feature matrix, as if it were a special feature value. The recognized syllable
features are <literal>&lt;syllable&gt;</literal>, <literal>&lt;onset&gt;</literal>, <literal>&lt;nucleus&gt;</literal>, and
<literal>&lt;coda&gt;</literal>. For example, the following rule devoices non-sonorant obstruents
in coda positions:</para>
        <screen>
rule coda-devoice
    [-son +cons &lt;coda&gt;] =&gt; [-vc]
</screen>
        <para>In the same vein, the following rule ensures that all nuclear segments are
marked as <literal>+syll</literal>:</para>
        <screen>
rule nucleus-syllabic
    [&lt;nucleus&gt;] =&gt; [+syll]
</screen>
        <para>The syllable features <literal>&lt;onset&gt;</literal>, <literal>&lt;nucleus&gt;</literal>, and <literal>&lt;coda&gt;</literal> work
exactly as expected, matching any segment which is assigned to the onset,
nucleus, and coda portions of the syllable, respectively. The <literal>&lt;syllable&gt;</literal>
feature matches any segment that has been assigned to any syllable, and fails
to match only when the segment in question is unsyllabified.</para>
        <para>There are also features that match segments <emphasis>not</emphasis> in a particular syllable
portion, marked with an asterisk (<literal>*</literal>) inside the angle brackets, as with
null feature values: <literal>&lt;*onset&gt;</literal>, <literal>&lt;*nucleus&gt;</literal>, <literal>&lt;*coda&gt;</literal>, and
<literal>&lt;*syllable&gt;</literal>. The following rule deletes segments which could not be
assigned to any syllable:</para>
        <screen>
rule delete-unsyllabified
    [&lt;*syllable&gt;] =&gt; *
</screen>
        <para>Likewise, the following inserts an epenthetic /i/ before unsyllabified
consonants:</para>
        <screen>
rule epenthetic-i
    * =&gt; i / _ [+cons &lt;*syllable&gt;]
</screen>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 label="3.6" id="Imports">
      <title>Imports</title>
      <para>You can include Phonix files from other Phonix files using the <literal>import</literal>
command. There are also several built-in resources that you can use, which are
covered in this section.</para>

      <sect2 label="3.6.1" id="Importing-files">
        <title>Importing files</title>
        <para>You may import one Phonix file into another with the following declaration:</para>
        <screen>
import <replaceable>filename</replaceable>
</screen>
        <para>The <firstterm>filename</firstterm> given to the import command follows the same rules as other
Phonix strings, which means that you need to quote it if it contains certain
characters that have special meaning for Phonix. For details, See <xref linkend="Strings"></xref>.
Examples:</para>
        <screen>
import other-phonology.phonix
import "/home/linguist/latin.phonix"
import "C:\greek.phonix"
</screen>
        <para>If the file name that you give after <literal>import</literal> is not an absolute path,
Phonix looks for the file you imported in the following places:</para>
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <para>In the current directory.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the same directory as the Phonix file currently being parsed (if that
directory is different from the current directory).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>In a named resource.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The <firstterm>named resources</firstterm> that Phonix looks for are special "filenames" that
represent built-in feature or symbol sets meant to simplify common linguistic
tasks. The following sections describe these resources.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.6.2" id="@code{std.features}">
        <title><literal>std.features</literal></title>
        <para>The standard feature set contains the commonly used features that you probably
learned about in your introductory Phonology class. You include the standard
feature set by writing <literal>import std.features</literal>. All of the features in the
standard set are binary features given in their abbreviated forms. The features
are gathered into a feature tree following this naming convention: leaf
features are written in lower case, node features are written in initial caps,
and the <literal>ROOT</literal> feature is written in all caps. The tree has the following
structure:</para>
        <screen>
+ROOT
    +Place
        +Labial
            -ro
        +Coronal
            -ant
            -dist
        +Dorsal
            -hi
            -lo
            -bk
            -fr
    +Glottal
        -vc
        -sg
        -cg
    +Manner
        -cont
        -nas
        -str
        -lat
        -dr
        +Class
            -cons
            -syll
            -son
</screen>
        <para>The <literal>std.features</literal> file itself looks like this:</para>
        <screen>
<screen># Segment classes
feature cons    # consonantal
feature son     # sonorant
feature syll    # syllabic
feature Class (type=node children=cons,son,syll)

# Glottal features
feature vc      # voice
feature sg      # spread glottis
feature cg      # constricted glottis
feature Glottal (type=node children=vc,sg,cg)

# Manner of articulation
feature cont    # continuant
feature nas     # nasal
feature str     # strident
feature lat     # lateral
feature dr      # delayed-release
feature Manner (type=node children=cont,nas,str,lat,dr,Class)

# Labial features
feature ro      # round
feature Labial (type=node children=ro)

# Coronal features
feature ant     # anterior
feature dist    # distributed
feature Coronal (type=node children=ant,dist)

# Dorsal features
feature hi      # high
feature lo      # low
feature bk      # back
feature fr      # front
feature Dorsal (type=node children=hi,lo,bk,fr)

# The Place node governs all place-of-articulation features
feature Place (type=node children=Labial,Coronal,Dorsal)

# The ROOT node governs all features
feature ROOT (type=node children=Place,Glottal,Manner,Class)
</screen></screen>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.6.3" id="@code{std.symbols}">
        <title><literal>std.symbols</literal></title>
        <para>The standard symbol set contains over 100 phonetic symbols that you can use for
input and output. In order to use the standard symbol set, you have to first
import the standard feature set <literal>std.features</literal>, since the standard symbols
depend on the features defined in that set. You include the standard symbols by
writing <literal>import std.symbols</literal>. The standard symbol set uses only 7-bit ASCII
characters and is based on the X-SAMPA IPA encoding.</para>
        <screen>
<screen>### CONSONANTS ###

## Obstruents ##

# Labial #

symbol p   [+cons -son -cont -vc -ro]
symbol p\  [+cons -son +cont -str -vc -ro]
symbol f   [+cons -son +cont +str -vc -ro]
symbol b   [+cons -son -cont +vc -ro]
symbol B   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc -ro]
symbol v   [+cons -son +cont +str +vc -ro]

# Dental #

symbol T   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc +ant +dist]
symbol D   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc +ant +dist]

# Alveolar #

symbol t   [+cons -son -cont -vc +ant -dist]
symbol s   [+cons -son +cont +str -vc +ant -dist]
symbol d   [+cons -son -cont +vc +ant -dist]
symbol z   [+cons -son +cont +str +vc +ant -dist]

# Palatal #

symbol c   [+cons -son -cont -vc -ant +dist]
symbol C   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc -ant +dist]
symbol S   [+cons -son +cont +str -vc -ant +dist]
symbol J\  [+cons -son -cont +vc -ant +dist]
symbol j\  [+cons -son +cont -str +vc -ant +dist]
symbol Z   [+cons -son +cont +str +vc -ant +dist]

# Retroflex #

symbol t`  [+cons -son -cont -vc -ant -dist]
symbol s`  [+cons -son +cont +str -vc -ant -dist]
symbol d`  [+cons -son -cont +vc -ant -dist]
symbol z`  [+cons -son +cont +str +vc -ant -dist]

# Velar #

symbol k   [+cons -son -cont -vc +bk -lo +hi]
symbol x   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc +bk -lo +hi]
symbol g   [+cons -son -cont +vc +bk -lo +hi]
symbol G   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc +bk -lo +hi]

# Uvular #

symbol q   [+cons -son -cont -vc +bk -lo -hi]
symbol X   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc +bk -lo -hi]
symbol G\  [+cons -son -cont +vc +bk -lo -hi]
symbol R   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc +bk -lo -hi]

# Pharyngeal #

symbol X\  [+cons -son +cont -str -vc +bk +lo -hi]
symbol ?\  [+cons -son +cont -str +vc +bk +lo -hi]

# Glottal #

symbol ?   [+cons -son -cont -vc]
symbol h   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc]
symbol h\  [+cons -son +cont -str +vc]

## Sonorants ##

# Labial #

symbol m   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat -ro]
symbol B\  [+cons +son +cont -nas -lat -ro]

# Alveolar #

symbol n   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat +ant -dist]
symbol l   [+cons +son -cont -nas +lat +ant -dist]
symbol 4   [+cons +son -cont -nas -lat +ant -dist]
symbol r   [+cons +son +cont -nas -lat +ant -dist]
symbol r\  [-cons +son +cont -nas -lat +ant -dist]

# Retroflex #

symbol n`  [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat -ant -dist]
symbol l`  [+cons +son -cont -nas +lat -ant -dist]

# Postalveolar #

symbol J   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat -ant +dist]
symbol L   [+cons +son -cont -nas +lat -ant +dist]

# Velar #

symbol N   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat +bk -lo +hi]
symbol L\  [+cons +son -cont -nas +lat +bk -lo +hi]

# Uvular #

symbol N\  [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat +bk -lo -hi]
symbol R\  [+cons +son +cont -nas -lat +bk -lo -hi]

### Vocoids ###

## Vowels ##

# High tense #

symbol i   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +str]
symbol y   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol 1   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk +hi -lo +str]
symbol }   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk +hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol M   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk +hi -lo +str]
symbol u   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk +hi -lo +ro +str]

# High lax #

symbol I   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk +hi -lo -str]
symbol Y   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +ro -str]
symbol I\  [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk +hi -lo -str]
symbol U\  [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk +hi -lo +ro -str]
symbol U   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk +hi -lo +ro -str]

# High mid #

symbol e   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk -hi -lo +str]
symbol 2   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk -hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol @\  [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi -lo +str]
symbol 8   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol 7   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi -lo +str]
symbol o   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi -lo +ro +str]

# Schwa #

symbol @   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi -lo -str]

# Open mid #

symbol E   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk -hi -lo -str]
symbol 9   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk -hi -lo +ro -str]
# Omitted: /3/, which is identical, feature-wise to /@/
symbol 3\  [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi -lo +ro -str]
symbol V   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi -lo -str]
symbol O   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi -lo +ro -str]

# Open lax #

symbol {   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi +lo -str]
symbol 6   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi +lo -str]

# Open #

symbol a   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi +lo +str]
symbol &amp;   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi +lo -ro +str]
symbol A   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi +lo +str]
symbol Q   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi +lo -ro +str]

## Semivowels ##

symbol j   [-cons +son -syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +str]
symbol H   [-cons +son -syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol w   [-cons +son -syll -fr +bk +hi -lo +ro +str]
</screen></screen>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.6.4" id="@code{std.symbols.diacritics}">
        <title><literal>std.symbols.diacritics</literal></title>
        <para>The standard diacritic set includes diacritics intended for use with
<literal>std.symbols</literal>. These diacritics are 7-bit ASCII characters based on the
X-SAMPA IPA encoding.</para>
        <screen>
<screen>## Consonant place modifiers ##

# Labialized
symbol '_w'    (diacritic) [-ro]

# Linguolabial
symbol '_N'    (diacritic) [-ro +ant]

# Dental
symbol '_d'    (diacritic) [+ant +dist]

# Palatalized
symbol '_j'    (diacritic) [-ant +dist]

# Velarized
symbol '_G'    (diacritic) [+bk +hi]

# Pharyngealized
symbol '_?\'   (diacritic) [+bk +lo]

## Vocoid modifiers ##

# Advanced
symbol '_+'    (diacritic) [+fr]

# Retracted
symbol '_-'    (diacritic) [+bk]

# Lowered
symbol '_o'    (diacritic) [+lo]

# Raised
symbol '_r'    (diacritic) [+hi]

# Centralized
symbol '_"'    (diacritic) [-hi -lo -fr -bk]

## Manner modifiers ##

# Voiceless
symbol '_0'    (diacritic) [-vc]

# Voiced
symbol '_v'    (diacritic) [+vc]

# Syllabic
symbol '='     (diacritic) [+syll]

# Non-syllabic
symbol '_^'    (diacritic) [-syll]

# Nasalized
symbol ~       (diacritic) [+nas]
</screen></screen>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.6.5" id="@code{std.symbols.ipa}">
        <title><literal>std.symbols.ipa</literal></title>
        <para>The IPA symbol set contains the same notional symbols as <literal>std.symbols</literal>,
but it uses IPA Unicode characters instead of ASCII X-SAMPA. To use the IPA
symbol set, write <literal>import std.features</literal> and <literal>import std.symbols.ipa</literal>
at the top of your file.</para>
        <screen>
<screen>### CONSONANTS ###

## Obstruents ##

# Labial #

symbol p   [+cons -son -cont -vc -ro]
symbol É¸   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc -ro]
symbol f   [+cons -son +cont +str -vc -ro]
symbol b   [+cons -son -cont +vc -ro]
symbol Î²   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc -ro]
symbol v   [+cons -son +cont +str +vc -ro]

# Dental #

symbol Î¸   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc +ant +dist]
symbol Ã°   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc +ant +dist]

# Alveolar #

symbol t   [+cons -son -cont -vc +ant -dist]
symbol s   [+cons -son +cont +str -vc +ant -dist]
symbol d   [+cons -son -cont +vc +ant -dist]
symbol z   [+cons -son +cont +str +vc +ant -dist]

# Palatal #

symbol c   [+cons -son -cont -vc -ant +dist]
symbol Ã§   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc -ant +dist]
symbol Êƒ   [+cons -son +cont +str -vc -ant +dist]
symbol ÉŸ   [+cons -son -cont +vc -ant +dist]
symbol Ê   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc -ant +dist]
symbol Ê’   [+cons -son +cont +str +vc -ant +dist]

# Retroflex #

symbol Êˆ   [+cons -son -cont -vc -ant -dist]
symbol Ê‚   [+cons -son +cont +str -vc -ant -dist]
symbol É–   [+cons -son -cont +vc -ant -dist]
symbol Ê   [+cons -son +cont +str +vc -ant -dist]

# Velar #

symbol k   [+cons -son -cont -vc +bk -lo +hi]
symbol x   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc +bk -lo +hi]
symbol g   [+cons -son -cont +vc +bk -lo +hi]
symbol É£   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc +bk -lo +hi]

# Uvular #

symbol q   [+cons -son -cont -vc +bk -lo -hi]
symbol Ï‡   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc +bk -lo -hi]
symbol É¢   [+cons -son -cont +vc +bk -lo -hi]
symbol Ê   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc +bk -lo -hi]

# Pharyngeal #

symbol Ä§   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc +bk +lo -hi]
symbol Ê•   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc +bk +lo -hi]

# Glottal #

symbol Ê”   [+cons -son -cont -vc]
symbol h   [+cons -son +cont -str -vc]
symbol É¦   [+cons -son +cont -str +vc]

## Sonorants ##

# Labial #

symbol m   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat -ro]
symbol Ê™   [+cons +son +cont -nas -lat -ro]

# Alveolar #

symbol n   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat +ant -dist]
symbol l   [+cons +son -cont -nas +lat +ant -dist]
symbol É¾   [+cons +son -cont -nas -lat +ant -dist]
symbol r   [+cons +son +cont -nas -lat +ant -dist]
symbol É¹   [-cons +son +cont -nas -lat +ant -dist]

# Retroflex #

symbol É³   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat -ant -dist]
symbol É­   [+cons +son -cont -nas +lat -ant -dist]

# Postalveolar #

symbol É²   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat -ant +dist]
symbol ÊŽ   [+cons +son -cont -nas +lat -ant +dist]

# Velar #

symbol Å‹   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat +bk -lo +hi]
symbol ÊŸ   [+cons +son -cont -nas +lat +bk -lo +hi]

# Uvular #

symbol É´   [+cons +son -cont +nas -lat +bk -lo -hi]
symbol Ê€   [+cons +son +cont -nas -lat +bk -lo -hi]

### Vocoids ###

## Vowels ##

# High tense #

symbol i   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +str]
symbol y   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol É¨   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk +hi -lo +str]
symbol Ê‰   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk +hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol É¯   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk +hi -lo +str]
symbol u   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk +hi -lo +ro +str]

# High lax #

symbol Éª   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk +hi -lo -str]
symbol Ê   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +ro -str]
symbol áµ»   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk +hi -lo -str]
symbol áµ¿   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk +hi -lo +ro -str]
symbol ÊŠ   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk +hi -lo +ro -str]

# High mid #

symbol e   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk -hi -lo +str]
symbol Ã¸   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk -hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol É˜   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi -lo +str]
symbol Éµ   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol É¤   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi -lo +str]
symbol o   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi -lo +ro +str]

# Schwa #

symbol É™   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi -lo -str]

# Open mid #

symbol É›   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk -hi -lo -str]
symbol Å“   [-cons +son +syll +fr -bk -hi -lo +ro -str]
# Omitted: /Éœ/, which is identical, feature-wise to /É™/
symbol Éž   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi -lo +ro -str]
symbol ÊŒ   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi -lo -str]
symbol É”   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi -lo +ro -str]

# Open lax #

symbol Ã¦   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi +lo -str]
symbol É   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi +lo -str]

# Open #

symbol a   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi +lo +str]
symbol É¶   [-cons +son +syll -fr -bk -hi +lo -ro +str]
symbol É‘   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi +lo +str]
symbol É’   [-cons +son +syll -fr +bk -hi +lo -ro +str]

## Semivowels ##

symbol j   [-cons +son -syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +str]
symbol É¥   [-cons +son -syll +fr -bk +hi -lo +ro +str]
symbol w   [-cons +son -syll -fr +bk +hi -lo +ro +str]
</screen></screen>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="3.6.6" id="@code{std.symbols.ipa.diacritics}">
        <title><literal>std.symbols.ipa.diacritics</literal></title>
        <para>This set contains IPA diacritics for use with <literal>std.symbols.ipa</literal>. The
diacritics contained here are the same as those in
<literal>std.symbols.diacritics</literal>, but rendered in IPA Unicode.</para>
        <screen>
<screen>## Consonant place modifiers ##

# Labialized
symbol Ê·       (diacritic) [-ro]

# Linguolabial
symbol Ì¼        (diacritic) [-ro +ant]

# Dental
symbol Ìª        (diacritic) [+ant +dist]

# Palatalized
symbol Ê²       (diacritic) [-ant +dist]

# Velarized
symbol Ì´        (diacritic) [+bk +hi]

# Pharyngealized
symbol Ë¤       (diacritic) [+bk +lo]

## Vocoid modifiers ##

# Advanced
symbol ÌŸ        (diacritic) [+fr]

# Retracted
symbol Ì         (diacritic) [+bk]

# Lowered
symbol Ìž        (diacritic) [+lo]

# Raised
symbol Ì        (diacritic) [+hi]

# Centralized
symbol Ìˆ        (diacritic) [-hi -lo -fr -bk]

## Manner modifiers ##

# Voiceless
symbol Ì¥        (diacritic) [-vc]

# Voiced
symbol Ì¬        (diacritic) [+vc]

# Syllabic
symbol Ì©        (diacritic) [+syll]

# Non-syllabic
symbol Ì¯        (diacritic) [-syll]

# Nasalized
symbol Ìƒ        (diacritic) [+nas]
</screen></screen>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 label="3.7" id="Comments">
      <title>Comments</title>
      <para>In Phonix the comment character is <literal>#</literal>. Everything from <literal>#</literal> to the
end of a line is a comment and is silently ignored by Phonix (unless the
<literal>#</literal> character is embedded in a string). For example:</para>
      <screen>
# This is a comment
feature ex # this comment explains what 'ex' means
</screen>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 label="3.8" id="Strings">
      <title>Strings</title>
      <para>Any time that Phonix expects you to provide a string, as for feature names,
symbols, or rule names, you can type almost anything you want.  The only
exception is if the contents of the string somehow confuse the Phonix compiler.
Don't do that. Everything else is fine.</para>
      <para>The long, boring, technical version follows.</para>
      <para>Phonix recognizes two types of strings: <firstterm>bare</firstterm> strings and <firstterm>quoted</firstterm>
strings. Most of the time you can use bare strings, which keeps your Phonix
file nice and uncluttered. The rules for bare strings are extremely forgiving,
to minimize the situation where you have to use a quoted string:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A bare string cannot contain whitespace. More specifically, whitespace is
always interpreted as a token delimiter outside of a quoted string, which
implicitly means it cannot be part of a string.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A bare string cannot contain any of the characters <literal>[]()&lt;&gt;$=</literal> <emphasis>at
all</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A bare string cannot begin with any of the characters <literal>+-*/#_"'</literal>.
However, these characters can appear in the middle of strings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>This should be enough for almost all cases, but in case it's not, you can also
create a quoted string by surrounding a string with single quotes (<literal>'</literal>) or
double quotes (<literal>"</literal>). If you are using a quoted string in a rule or a
symbol declaration, the opening quote must be preceded by a space. Anything at
all can appear inside a quoted string, except for another quote, of course.
There is no mechanism for escaping quotes, so if you need to include a single
quote then surround your quote with double quotes, and vice versa.</para>
      <para>The following are valid strings that could be used for feature names, rule
names, or symbols:</para>
      <screen>
foo
foo-bar
foo+
bar?
!
b*a*z
blu"
"+++"
'_'
'"'
</screen>
      <para>The following are NOT valid strings and cannot be used for feature names, rule
names, or symbols:</para>
      <screen>
-foo        # looks like a feature value
_foo        # ambiguous in rule context
foo()       # cannot use parentheses
foo$        # cannot use dollar sign
</screen>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter label="4" id="Examples">
    <title>Examples</title>
    <para>The following examples illustrate common use cases for Phonix.</para>

    <sect1 label="4.1" id="Romanian">
      <title>Romanian</title>
      <para>The following files define a phonology for contemporary Romanian, and
illustrates how most of the surface alternations in Romanian can be derived.
Note that the example is somewhat incomplete: the input represents an internal
reconstruction of Proto-Romanian, not Proto-Romance or Vulgar Latin, and there
may be a few alternations that slipped by. However, the majority of the active
phonological processes in Romanian should be represented.</para>

      <sect2 label="4.1.1">
        <title><filename>romanian.phonix</filename></title>
        <screen>
<screen>import std.features

# 
# We add a feature for stress, which is important for many rules
#
feature stress

#
# We create our own symbol set, defining only Romanian phonemes
#

# Unstressed vowels
symbol a  [+syll -cons +son -hi +lo -fr -bk -stress]
symbol e  [+syll -cons +son -hi -lo +fr -bk -stress]
symbol o  [+syll -cons +son -hi -lo -fr +bk +ro -stress]
symbol @  [+syll -cons +son -hi -lo -fr -bk -stress]
symbol i  [+syll -cons +son +hi -lo +fr -bk -stress]
symbol u  [+syll -cons +son +hi -lo -fr +bk +ro -stress]
symbol 1  [+syll -cons +son +hi -lo -fr -bk -stress]

# Stress diacritic
symbol "'"  (diacritic) [+stress]

# Non-syllabic vocoids
symbol j  [-syll -cons +son +hi -lo +fr -bk -stress]
symbol w  [-syll -cons +son +hi -lo -fr +bk +ro -stress]

# Non-syllabic diacritic
symbol `  (diacritic) [-syll]

# Labials
symbol p  [+cons +ro -son]
symbol b  [+cons +ro -son +vc]
symbol f  [+cons +ro -son +cont]
symbol v  [+cons +ro -son +cont +vc]
symbol m  [+cons +ro +son +nas]

# Dentals
symbol t  [+cons +ant -son]
symbol ts  [+cons +ant -son +dr]
symbol d  [+cons +ant -son +vc]
symbol dz  [+cons +ant -son +dr +vc]
symbol s  [+cons +cont -son +ant]
symbol z  [+cons +cont -son +ant +vc]
symbol n  [+cons +ant +son +nas]
symbol l  [+cons +ant +son +lat]
symbol r  [+cons +ant +son +cont]

# Palatals
symbol tS  [+cons -son -ant +dist +dr]
symbol dZ  [+cons -son -ant +dist +vc +dr]
symbol S  [+cons -son -ant +cont +dist]
symbol Z  [+cons -son -ant +cont +dist +vc]

# Velars
symbol k  [+cons -son +hi]
symbol g  [+cons -son +hi +vc]
symbol h  [+cons -son +hi +cont]

#
# Here we begin with the rules
#

# Reduce i/u to semivowels where appropriate
rule make-semivowels
[+hi +syll] =&gt; [-syll] / [+syll] _

# Stress all penult syllables. This rule illustrates two interesting
# techniques. First, it specifies a filter of [+syll], which means that the
# rule only "sees" [+syll] segments. Second, it uses an empty set of braces []
# to match "any segment".
rule stress-penult (filter=[+syll])
[] =&gt; [+stress] / _ [] $

# When the antepenult syllable is lexically stressed, remove stress on the
# penult syllable. 
rule stress-antepenult (filter=[+syll])
[+stress] =&gt; [-stress] / [+stress] _

# Break word-initial /e/
rule initial-iotacization
* =&gt; j / $ _ [+fr -hi -lo]

# Palatalize velars before front vowels
rule palatalize-velars
[+cons +hi] =&gt; [-ant +dist +dr *hi] / _ [+fr]

# Palatalize dental fricatives before high front vowels
rule palatalize-dentals
[+cons +ant +cont -son] =&gt; [-ant +dist] / _ [+hi +fr]

# Assimilate palatalization
rule assimilate-palatals
[+cons -son *ro] =&gt; [-ant +dist] / _ [-ant +dist]

# Affricate dental stops before /i/
rule affricate-dentals
[+cons +ant -son] =&gt; [+dr] / _ i

# Simplify /dz/
rule simplify-dz
dz =&gt; z

# Simplify /StS/ everywhere
rule simplify-StS
StS =&gt; St

# Change velar+/l/ to a palatalized velar
rule l-palatalize
l =&gt; j / [+cons +hi] _

# Raise stressed central vowels before /n/
rule prenasal-raising
[-hi -lo +stress] =&gt; [+hi] / _ n

# Centralize front non-high vowels after labials
rule postlabial-centralize
[-hi +fr] =&gt; [-fr] / [+ro] _

# Front central vowels when the next vowel is a front vowel
rule front-assimilation (filter=[-cons])
[-fr -bk -lo] =&gt; [+fr] / _ [+fr]

# Raise unstressed /o/
rule o-raising (filter=[+syll])
o =&gt; u / _ [+stress]

# Drop word-final /u/
rule drop-final-u
u =&gt; * / _ $

# Desyllabify word-final /i/
rule desyllabify-final-i
i =&gt; j / _ $

# Centralize unstressed /a/, except when /a/ is the first segment
rule centralize-a
a =&gt; @ / [] _

# Centralize /a/ in the 1pl verbal ending
rule centralize-1pl-a
a' =&gt; @' / _m $

# Break stressed mid vowels into semivowel + a when the next syllable contains
# a non-high vowel
rule breaking (filter=[+syll])
[-hi -lo +stress] * =&gt; [-syll -stress] a' / _ [-hi *ro]

# Assimilate /ea/ followed by /e/
rule assimilate-ea (filter=[-cons])
e`a' =&gt; e' * / _ e

# Assimilate /oa/ followed by /w/
rule assimilate-oa
o`a' =&gt; o' * / _ w

# Assimilate semivowels after a palatal
rule assimilate-postpalatal-semivowel
[-syll +fr] =&gt; * / [+dr +dist] _

# Assimilate consecutive semivowels of the same frontness
rule assimilate-consecutive-semivowel
[-syll $fr] =&gt; * / [-syll $fr] _

# Assimilate coronal sonorants before /j/
rule assimilate-sonorants
[+cons +ant +son *cont] =&gt; * / _ j

# Drop non-syllabic central vowels
rule drop-central-vocoids
[-fr -bk -syll] =&gt; *
</screen></screen>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 label="4.1.2">
        <title>Input and output</title>
        <para>You can generate the output file with the following command line:</para>
        <screen>
phonix romanian.phonix -i romanian.input -o romanian.output
</screen>
        <para>The following table shows the input and the generated output together with the
output form in Romanian orthography.</para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colwidth="25*"></colspec>
            <colspec colwidth="25*"></colspec>
            <colspec colwidth="50*"></colspec>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Input</entry>
                <entry>Output</entry>
                <entry>Orthography</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vedu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>v@'d</literal></entry>
                <entry>vÄƒd</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vedi</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>ve'zj</literal></entry>
                <entry>vezi</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vede</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>ve'de</literal></entry>
                <entry>vede</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vedemu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>vede'm</literal></entry>
                <entry>vedem</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vedeti</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>vede'tsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>vedeÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vedu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>v@'d</literal></entry>
                <entry>vÄƒd</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>veda</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>va'd@</literal></entry>
                <entry>vadÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vezutu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>v@zu't</literal></entry>
                <entry>vÄƒzut</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>venu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>vi'n</literal></entry>
                <entry>vin</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>veni</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>vi'j</literal></entry>
                <entry>vii</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vene</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>vi'ne</literal></entry>
                <entry>vine</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>venimu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>veni'm</literal></entry>
                <entry>venim</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>veniti</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>veni'tsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>veniÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>venu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>vi'n</literal></entry>
                <entry>vin</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>vena</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>vi'n@</literal></entry>
                <entry>vinÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>venitu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>veni't</literal></entry>
                <entry>venit</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>esu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>je's</literal></entry>
                <entry>ies</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>esi</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>je'Sj</literal></entry>
                <entry>ieÅŸi</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>ese</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>je'se</literal></entry>
                <entry>iese</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>esimu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>jeSi'm</literal></entry>
                <entry>ieÅŸim</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>esiti</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>jeSi'tsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>ieÅŸiÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>esu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>je's</literal></entry>
                <entry>ies</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>esa</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>ja's@</literal></entry>
                <entry>iasÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>esitu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>jeSi't</literal></entry>
                <entry>ieÅŸit</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>potu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po't</literal></entry>
                <entry>pot</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>poti</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po'tsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>poÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>pote</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po`a'te</literal></entry>
                <entry>poate</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>potemu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>pute'm</literal></entry>
                <entry>putem</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>poteti</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>pute'tsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>puteÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>potu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po't</literal></entry>
                <entry>pot</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>pota</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po`a't@</literal></entry>
                <entry>poatÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>potutu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>putu't</literal></entry>
                <entry>putut</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>keru</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>tSe'r</literal></entry>
                <entry>cer</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>keri</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>tSe'rj</literal></entry>
                <entry>ceri</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>kere</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>tSe're</literal></entry>
                <entry>cere</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>ke'remu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>tSe'rem</literal></entry>
                <entry>cerem</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>ke'reti</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>tSe'retsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>cereÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>keru</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>tSe'r</literal></entry>
                <entry>cer</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>kera</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>tSa'r@</literal></entry>
                <entry>cearÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>kerutu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>tSeru't</literal></entry>
                <entry>cerut</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>portu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po'rt</literal></entry>
                <entry>port</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>porti</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po'rtsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>porÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>porta</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po`a'rt@</literal></entry>
                <entry>poartÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>portamu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>purt@'m</literal></entry>
                <entry>purtÄƒm</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>portati</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>purta'tsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>purtaÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>porta</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po`a'rt@</literal></entry>
                <entry>poartÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>porte</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>po`a'rte</literal></entry>
                <entry>poarte</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>portatu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>purta't</literal></entry>
                <entry>purtat</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>freku</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>fre'k</literal></entry>
                <entry>frec</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>freki</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>fre'tS</literal></entry>
                <entry>freci</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>freka</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>fre`a'k@</literal></entry>
                <entry>freacÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>frekamu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>frek@'m</literal></entry>
                <entry>frecÄƒm</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>frekati</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>freka'tsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>frecaÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>freka</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>fre`a'k@</literal></entry>
                <entry>freacÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>freke</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>fre'tSe</literal></entry>
                <entry>frece</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>klemu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>kje'm</literal></entry>
                <entry>chem</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>klemi</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>kje'mj</literal></entry>
                <entry>chemi</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>klema</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>kja'm@</literal></entry>
                <entry>cheamÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>klemamu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>kjem@'m</literal></entry>
                <entry>chemÄƒm</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>klemati</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>kjema'tsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>chemaÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>klema</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>kja'm@</literal></entry>
                <entry>cheamÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>kleme</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>kja'm@</literal></entry>
                <entry>cheamÄƒ *Note that this is the regular outcome of the sound change, but this form (the 3rd person subjunctive) has been analogically restored to 'cheme' in the standard language.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>kalu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>ka'l</literal></entry>
                <entry>cal</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>kali</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>ka'j</literal></entry>
                <entry>cai</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>udu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>u'd</literal></entry>
                <entry>ud</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>uda</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>u'd@</literal></entry>
                <entry>udÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>ude</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>u'de</literal></entry>
                <entry>ude</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>udi</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>u'zj</literal></entry>
                <entry>uzi</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>pro'spetu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>pro`a'sp@t</literal></entry>
                <entry>proaspÄƒt</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>pro'speta</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>pro`a'sp@t@</literal></entry>
                <entry>proaspÄƒtÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>pro'speti</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>pro`a'spetsj</literal></entry>
                <entry>proaspeÅ£i</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>pro'spete</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>pro`a'spete</literal></entry>
                <entry>proaspete</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>osu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>o's</literal></entry>
                <entry>os</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>ose</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>o`a'se</literal></entry>
                <entry>oase</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>oie</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>o`a'je</literal></entry>
                <entry>oaie</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>oi</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>oj</literal></entry>
                <entry>oi</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>ou</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>ow</literal></entry>
                <entry>ou</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>oue</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>o'w@</literal></entry>
                <entry>ouÄƒ</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>peske</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>pe'Ste</literal></entry>
                <entry>peÅŸte</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>peski</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>pe'Stj</literal></entry>
                <entry>peÅŸti</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>oklu</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>o'kj</literal></entry>
                <entry>ochi</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>okli</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>o'kj</literal></entry>
                <entry>ochi</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry><literal>klaru</literal></entry>
                <entry><literal>kja'r</literal></entry>
                <entry>chiar</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <appendix id="License">
    <title>License</title>
    <para>This is the license for the Phonix Phonological Transformation
Language, the program `phonix.exe' in source and binary forms, and for
the Phonix manual.</para>
    <para>Copyright (C) 2009 Jesse Bangs All rights reserved.</para>
    <para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are
met:</para>
    <para>* Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
* notice, this
list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</para>
    <para>* Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
* notice, this
list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</para>
    <para>* Neither the name of Jesse Bangs nor the names of its contributors
* may be
used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without
specific prior written permission.</para>
    <para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS
"AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR
A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL,
SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT
LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY
THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
(INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE
OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
  </appendix>
</book>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-indent-data:nil
End:
-->
